<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
    <channel>
        <title>Bruno Pettersen-Coulombe Blog</title>
        <link>https://brunopc.net/blog</link>
        <description>Bruno Pettersen-Coulombe Blog</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Tue, 25 Jul 2023 00:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Do you really need the complete stack?]]></title>
            <link>https://brunopc.net/blog/2023/07/25/Do-you-really-need-the-complete-stack</link>
            <guid>https://brunopc.net/blog/2023/07/25/Do-you-really-need-the-complete-stack</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 25 Jul 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Useful or useless?]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img loading="lazy" alt="Useful or useless?" src="/assets/images/useful-or-useless-82f72b3b335c2d9c5699d12355a19ffd.webp" width="1000" height="641" class="img_ev3q"></p><p>While thining about this blog, my initial plan was to use <a href="https://wordpress.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Wordpress</a>. After all, I was familiar with the platform, having worked with PHP in the past. People generally dislike unnecessary changes, and I'm no alien. However, upon reflecting on my past experiences with WordPress, I realized it had its drawbacks. It wasn't free since I had to purchase a web hosting plan and manage the hosting myself. Additionally, there were frequent updates and security vulnerabilities to patch. Although it seemed wonderful initially, over time, the operational burdens increased significantly. Eventually, I stopped blogging because it became costly in terms of both money and energy.</p><p>After this reflection, I began searching for alternatives. Was there a better solution out there? That's when I came across <a href="https://jekyllrb.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Jekyll</a> and decided to experiment with it. It appeared to be a great idea: no databases, no updates to worry about, just plain text content. The ability to post for free on Github Pages, with the option of a custom domain and without mandatory ads, was very appealing. It was simple, easy, and extremely stable. The very idea of just having to write plain-text Markdown files felt like using my new 1Zpresso k-Max grinder after years of using a cheap grinder from Amazon. It just worked, and marvelously well.</p><p>The idea of static site generators (SSGs) was so impressive that other SSGs started emerging. One such SSG was Docusaurus, based on the popular front-end framework React. Since I was more familiar with JavaScript/React than Ruby, I felt that React, as an HTML frontend framework on its own, integrated perfectly as an SSG. Moreover, the fact that Docusaurus was backed up by Meta gave me confidence that it would be supported for a long time.I decided to give Docusaurus a try. </p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="ctco---cut-the-crap-out">CTCO - Cut the crap out<a href="#ctco---cut-the-crap-out" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to CTCO - Cut the crap out" title="Direct link to CTCO - Cut the crap out">​</a></h2><p>As humans, we can be peculiar at times. We try to solve one problem after another, but often, in doing so, we create more problems. Back then, I didn't need a database. Yes, it may have been "better" and "more technologically advanced" to use a DB instead of plain text HTML. However, in using a backend to manage the database, I needed a hosting plan. That hosting plan cost me money, which meant I had to work to pay for it. Essentially, I was working to buy myself more work. I did learn a lot, but I could have achieved more of what I really wanted at that time: establishing an online presence.</p><p>Having gained some experience in the industry now, I can say that many people tend to think that more is better. And it's not exclusive to software builders and managers. Asset manager Ben Carlson nailed it in his book <a href="http://www.amazon.ca/gp/product/1119024927/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=15121&amp;creative=390961&amp;creativeASIN=1119024927&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=canacoucpota-20" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">A Wealth of Common Sense</a>. Dan Bortolotti explains it well in his Canadian Couch Potato blog, in the post <a href="https://canadiancouchpotato.com/2016/01/25/why-simple-is-still-a-hard-sell/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><em>Why Simple Is Still a Hard Sell</em></a>:</p><blockquote><p>Ben Carlson <!-- -->[…]<!-- --> reveals that he’s made the same discovery: investors resist simplicity. Yet Carlson believes it’s the right solution for most of us. “I’ve spent my entire career working in portfolio management,” he writes. “This experience has taught me that less is always more when making investment decisions. Simplicity trumps complexity. Conventional gives you much better odds than exotic.”</p></blockquote><blockquote><p>A lot of complexity is just BS. “Complexity tends to be the default option that gets used to persuade investors to buy unnecessary investment products,” Carlson writes, “while the vast majority of people really just need to understand more conventional options to succeed.” When fund companies, media gurus and advisors peddle clever-sounding strategies, they’re creating “an illusion of intelligence and control.”</p></blockquote><p>I want to point out the fact that Software Engineering is still very immature. According to the <a href="https://vitalitychicago.com/blog/agile-projects-are-more-successful-traditional-projects/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Standish Group Chaos Report 2020</a>, only 42% of Agile projects and 13% of Waterfall projects were successful. In summary, the chances of a software project success (based on time, budget, target, goal, value, and user satisfaction) are still less than half, even when using agile methodologies And the more you simplify your solution, the lower the chances of complications.</p><p>What is your real goal? Do you want an illusion of control, or resolving the problem?</p><p>Personally, I choose the latter.</p>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>Wordpress</category>
            <category>PHP</category>
            <category>Jekyll</category>
            <category>Javascript</category>
            <category>React</category>
            <category>SSG</category>
            <category>Docusaurus</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Welcome, folks]]></title>
            <link>https://brunopc.net/blog/welcome</link>
            <guid>https://brunopc.net/blog/welcome</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 24 Jul 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[I was contemplating for a while about creating my own blog.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I was contemplating for a while about creating my own blog.</p><p>I like to write, as this form of communication is still the best we have to express an idea. Yes, spoken words have been increasing in popularity since podcasting became a thing. While I agree with Jordan Peterson that <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Dm9FaxV_RN4" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">spoken words are now more powerful then ever</a>, written words still have advantages - they are much better indexed by web crawlers. Additionally, as you can refine them multiple times before publishing, words will always be the most precise and structured way to express an idea. This is especially useful when you're in a very detailed field like programming.</p><p>A lot of developer blogs are written solely for other developers - a blog where you can find great code snippets, tutorials and such. However, developper blog targeted for a general audiance is far more rare. I think it's an angle that deserve to be better exploited - I've seen countless exemple of miscommunication between developper, managers, HR or marketing advisors. Even though Software Engineering have been around for some decades now, I think it's still pretty immature as for the understanding of the field by related departments. There's a lot of people that are lacking some knowledge to optimise their work with software teams.</p><p>This is the beginning of a journey. I don't know where it's gonna take me but I'm pretty sure it's gonna be great!</p><p>Long live the internet.</p>]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>